I think another doctor should do a video
about this one and add their name to the
title anyway if you're familiar with Dr
Mike iser tale from Renaissance
periodization you know full well this is
going to be a wild ride which also
includes a lot of cussing so just be
warned that Dr Mike wouldn't uh be
considered the most prim and proper
professional as we go through this
critique of Dr Oz's Miracle weight loss
being and you might be wondering what
I'll be doing well other than writing
the coat tales of Dr Mike and Dr Oz Dr
Nick will be presenting the data so that
you can be sure of what's right and
what's wrong because credentials are
cool but they aren't always Flawless as
we'll soon see and guess what I have the
study that Dr Oz uses for his claims and
you won't want to miss the punch line
because it's a doozy but let's begin
with letting Dr Mike introduce himself
so that you can uh get a flavor of
what's about to happen hey folks Dr Mike
here for Renaissance puration creator of
the RP hypertrophy app the RP diet coach
app and professor of exercise and sports
science at Leman College in the Bronx
hey the Bronx whoa off hey anyway that's
how I speak when I'm in the Bronx but I
also speak like that when confronted
with people making false claims about
diet and exercise that's right I get
quite hood and maybe nobody has made
more false claims in public and been
taken to a congressional hearing because
of it about nutrition and exercise
science in the most false way possible
than Mr Doctor Oz Dr Oz if you aren't
familiar has his medical doctorate as
well as a business degree and we'll see
which one of those wins out but for the
time being let's get into this miracle
weight false bead you may think magic is
make belief yes Magic is make belief
anyone after the age of eight is either
in that opinion or is deemed mentally
unwell but this little
bean a
bee hav eaten insects and bean bean
thanks got the video guy has scientist
saying they found a magic weight loss
cure for every body type wow I wonder
how many scientists have actually said
they found the magic weight loss cure
for every body type as a scientist let
me break this down for you nobody no
wait wait I Can Do Better Body types
aren't even a real thing magic isn't a
real thing and weight loss is not
something to be cured but to be treated
because you not acquire weight loss as
some kind of disease that occurs from a
pathogen or something like that finally
I'm cured of my weight loss no no excess
body weight is the thing you're actually
trying to cure if you were even going to
architect that position intelligently
Dr Oz yes I know you're an award-winning
heart surgeon or some like that but
your boy went to PhD in gym class and I
finished that about to critique you
more ah I'm already channeling Scott how
am I supposed to say it the duck
side I just wish I had a lightning bolt
to zap this dumb with you
feel
me okay we're off to
a start I'll leave the uh adjectives out
of this the world's largest scientific
Society triggered unprecedented
excitement for a weight loss study it
showed women and men you know thank God
and I thought it was only half of us
lost an astounding amount of fat and
weight 17 lbs in 22 weeks in disclosure
I skipped a lot of the comedic
commentary by Dr Mike because as
entertaining as he is we've got some
signs to get to so Dr Oz introduces this
study indicating this miracle Bean leads
to profound weight loss and by the way
that Miracle Bean is green coffee beans
let's hear more before we look at it for
ourselves weight loss Community is all
buzzing about
this I still want it to be a bee if he
had me eaten bees I'd be like I believe
it that's weird enough to work and
here's why the recent study that you
were talking about earlier they the the
participants took the capsules and they
did nothing else they didn't exercise
they didn't change their diet they
actually consumed 2400 calories a day I
don't understand how that's relevant but
please continue they burned only 400
calories now that's weight gain not
weight loss
what folks there is no one past the size
of a small child that has a resting
metabolic rate of less than 400 calories
so it is impossible for these people to
be burning less than 400 calories there
is no mathematical trickery going on
here this is at best a wild
misunderstanding of how reality works
and at worst a blatant life okay so I'm
inclined to agree having a metabolism of
400 calories even if you were to not
move because movement also contributes
significantly to Total metabolism is
literally impossible for any adult and
they lost over 10% of their total body
weight wait a minute 17
lb over 10% of their body weight that
means the average participant would have
to weigh less than 170
lb generally people in studies of drugs
or supplements that help people lose
weight are considerably overweight and
these people would not be again
nothing's adding up strange That's
mildly suspicious but you know what we
don't need to rely on speculation we can
open the study for ourselves it's this
one and if we pop open the data we can
see that these people were about 76 kg
or around 170 lb to Dr Mike's Point and
yet the results indicate that after the
study these participants did indeed lose
10% of their body weight and even that
pales in comparison to the fat loss over
15% so Dr O's guessed is correct that
these people lost the amount of weight
that they did oh I also forgot that
mention this but the previous point
about a 400 calorie metabolism is
nowhere to be found in the study we see
that the nutrition and the intake here
but there's no measure of total
metabolism anyway both sides are right
in their respective ways and they lost
about 17 pounds per participant and they
had no side effects zero side
effects okay so he was wrong earlier got
it thanks
we just throw make belie numbers out I
have to disagree with Dr Mike here
because the study does show as we saw
earlier a drop in body weight and we see
that it is around 8 kg or 17 lbs that
all checks out they also mentioned no
side effects and Dr Mike had this to say
by the way zero side effects is
every single study properly designed
collects side effects data and in every
single study just through statistical
noise you'll get people reporting a
certain number of side effects people
report uh gastrointestinal distress when
there's nothing happening to them in
reality they report headache in most
cases nausea and so on and so forth so
it's actually um very Unbecoming to say
there's no side effects you can say
minimal side effects you can say Trace
side effects no side effects well that's
exactly the kind of you'd
expect on a Dr O's Channel again the
researchers of this study do report no
adverse effects no side effects I agree
with Dr Mike that generally there is
some noise like some people start
complaining about certain things because
they're more attuned to it and then they
link it to what they're consuming but
that also assumes the number of
participants is high as in the odds of
one person will complain of a side
effect out of 1,000 is quite high but
this study was only 16 people so
although unlikely it's not impossible
that they didn't detect an effect or
it's also possible they didn't take a
proper record as how long do they have
to take the pills for they did it for 12
weeks only okay I'm no uh scientist but
earlier Scott the video guy didn't they
say 22
weeks 17 lbs in 22
weeks that's a good catch uh to clarify
the study was 22 weeks why wouldn't just
drinking coffee do this yeah because
because when the coffee that we drink is
roasted and when they roast it they
roast it at
475° F that sounds like a big number
that scares me it scares me too Dr Mike
I don't like big numbers like the number
22 but the most important thing it does
is it removes the chlorogenic acid
that's the key to what we're talking
about today you know I don't even know
what the chlorogenic acid is sounds made
up but it could be a real thing it
absolutely is possible that various
modifications made to food in the
Preparatory process such as the heating
of coffee can degrade some of the
phytochemicals and prevent them from
having positive effects or negative
effects on your body that's totally
plausible and so what this gentleman is
saying sounds plausible it's the results
that we're concerned about does it
really cause the things that he's
claiming I suspect the answer is no by
the way chlorogenic acid is a polyphenol
it's just a molecule that is linked to
having a heart protecting effect
however I can't or won't say you choose
which depending on how competent you
think I am if the coffee brewing process
actually eliminates the chlorogenic acid
the real answer is I don't know and it
doesn't matter here Dr Mike also
mentions that the product doesn't work
but as we saw from the study it does
seem to have an effect or does it well
stay tuned for that because there's
something a brewing and it ain't
chlorogenic acid less coffee so how does
it work well it's amazing it's what we
call a triple threat ah yes the triple
threat usually those win championships
yes that's what we typically say in
science triple threat it goes in and it
causes the body to burn glucose or sugar
and burn fat mainly in the liver he's
either phrasing this very poorly or he's
just making up the liver doesn't
burn a lot unless the liver metabolism
goes up and typically when your liver
metabolism goes up the doctors tell you
you're going to die really soon the
liver can liberate its glucose and fat
stores and release them into the
bloodstream maybe that's what he
means never can tell the second way and
the most important way is it slows the
release of sugar into the bloodstream
contradict my earlier point I just don't
know anything so when you don't have
sugar building up in the bloodstream you
don't have fat building up because sugar
turns to Fat I mean everybody knows that
this guy's a great public speaker he
could run for office um which Dr Oz
actually tried to do
recently um it reduces the amount of
sugar going into your
bloodstream somehow that's also supposed
to increase the amount of sugar you
burn yeah normally if you consume
carbohydrates or carbohydrates are
increased in the blood the cells of your
body generally turn to burning more
carbohydrates that's the same same as
sugar or glucose by the way at least in
a moderately healthy individual things
get a little more complicated in late
stages of diabetes for example and there
are several old studies on the topic
including this one as for the point
about sugar turning to Fat I know some
people disagree but that's because they
have zero clue what they're talking
about shots fired but sugar is minimally
turned into fat relative to the direct
fat storage from fat molecules
themselves anyway Dr Mike rants on for a
while especially with Dr Oz's Real
Results stories that he trots out but uh
let's get into some clarity uh we've had
enough fun first off Dr Mike is
hilarious let's just put that out of the
way he may not be everyone's cup of tea
not your cup of tea and I respect that
uh Second thing is when discussing
several aspects here he's dead on I
think I'd give a bit more credit to Dr
Oz when he gets things right because the
attempt at impartiality is important in
my mind and we saw that the study that
Dr Oz references does indicate the exact
numbers that he detailed by Dr Oz and
his guest but let's look at that study
just uh one more time okay so we see the
title and if we zoom out a little
whoops that can't be good that's right
the study was retracted which means that
we throw everything in it in the trash
so in the end Dr Mike was right it's all
Bs but does that mean that green coffee
bean isn't effective for weight loss
well actually not quite green coffee
bean extract does still have some
evidence pointing to it having a weight
loss effect yet the weight loss is
usually a lot less than Dr o touted more
in the ballpark of 2.5 kgs around 52 PBS
over several months too so yes Dr Oz
stretched the truth to put it mildly but
there might be some utility to coffee
bean extract regardless from my
perspective if I had to boil it down I
would stay away from Dr Oz's advice on
weight loss considering the uh well the
nonsense here and I probably wouldn't
worry about coffee bean extract because
black coffee itself is also known to
have a mild weight loss effect I hope it
helps and I do more science breakdowns
of popular Health influencers right here
FYI check it thanks for watching
[Music]